hello everyone and welcome to the
dissenter weekly update for January 3rd
2020 I'm Kevin gas Toula managing editor
for shadow proof comm we launched this
show in 2019 and each week we run down
the latest news and whistleblowing and
related press freedom stories we also
highlight developments with WikiLeaks
Julian Assange and Chelsea Manning on
today's show we welcome guest host John
Kiriakou he is a CIA whistleblower and a
former senior investigator with the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee he's
also a good friend of shadow proof
welcome to the show thank you so on
today's show we'll be talking about more
documents from WikiLeaks that expose
fraud in an OPCW investigation in Syria
as well as Trump's assassination of an
Iranian general and how that for that
pertains to the war on whistleblowers
but first we encourage viewers to hit
the red subscribe button below this
video to follow our show and remember
that shadow proof is a hundred percent
reader funded and supported website our
ability to do this show depend on your
financial support if you want to help us
sustain this show and grow as an
organization please donate or become a
member at shadow proof comm slash donate
so to begin we'll we'll do our first
topic which is related to Amazon and
critics who have been outspoken against
Amazon to Amazon employees were informed
they could be fired after they spoke out
against Amazon Marin Costa and Jaime
Kowalski previously said Amazon's cloud
computing business AIDS oil and gas
exploration customer called it was scary
to be called into a meeting like that
and then to be given a follow-up email
saying that if I continue to speak up I
can be fired but I spoke up because I'm
terrified by the harm the climate crisis
is already causing and I fear for my
children's future so Jon to you I mean
we've we've seen in the close of 2019
these horrific images from Australia of
the
brushfires we've seen other examples of
these natural disasters in the last year
or these natural occurrences that show
the effects and yet we have this major
mega corporation like Amazon cracking
down on employees freedom of speech yeah
this is a very disturbing development
inside a company that has already given
us lots of different reasons to be
concerned you know Amazon it was
reported just recently in the last
couple of months for example does oh
it's like we're having a connection
issue give its own employees a cup or a
jar and throw it away they're not even
allowed to go to the bathroom now here
we have an example of employees
reporting waste fraud abuse or
illegality the very definition of
whistleblowing
being threatened with the loss of their
employment and then the actual loss of
their employment following the the
warnings so yeah this is just another
reason to hate Amazon and companies like
Amazon and it's another reason to go to
our elected officials to complain
because there have to be protections and
and they have to be codified protections
for whistleblowers in corporate settings
as well as governmental all right thanks
for that John we're gonna go on to the
next story which involves a
whistleblower lawsuit in Pittsburgh
Jeremy Roe the CEO of the University of
Pittsburgh Medical Center has said that
he wants UPMC to become the
quote/unquote Amazon of health care and
in a recent development we saw in the
final week of 2019 that a whistleblower
lawsuit against UPMC neurosurgeons was
reinstated by a federal appeals court it
alleges starting in 2000 origins quote
inflated the number of spine operations
they did while performing needlessly
complex medical procedures to beef up
their earnings quote and that was in the
Pittsburgh post-gazette a local
newspaper again this shows the
profit motive in healthcare and how it
makes it really difficult for people to
guarantee that they're actually getting
the appropriate treatment they deserve
this is really an example of corporate
greed
I'm from the Pittsburgh area I was born
and raised in the Pittsburgh area I can
tell you that the University of
Pittsburgh Medical Center is one of the
most highly respected medical what can
you call it a conglomerate in the United
States on top of that the Pittsburgh
post-gazette is a very serious newspaper
it's a serious investigative journalism
site the pit party is telling us besides
the fact that there was this profit
motive and that that UPnP was trying to
maximize profits was that they were
purposely putting people's lives at risk
in order to maximize these profits that
it takes a certain kind of sickness I
believe I think this is a bigger story
than the national media has has given it
credit for being frankly the reporting
has pretty much only been in the
Pittsburgh post-gazette this is
something that needs to go national
because I believe it's indicative of a
bigger and broader problem throughout
healthcare
yeah and for those people who follow
whistleblowing issues closely they're
they're accused of violating kickback
statutes they're also accused of
violating the False Claims Act maybe you
have some knowledge of the False Claims
Act I know that this is a very useful
tool that people have used to are
interested in challenging the the
culture of fraud in this country seem to
be having a connection issue John yeah I
just got back I just heard you I got
most of your question yeah you know this
is exactly why the False Claims Act was
passed into law in the first place it
was to it to expose and to to out
organized I'm using the air quotes
around organized criminal activity when
it comes to inflating billing operations
so you know we
we go after we go after the Mafia for
example using Rico statutes well this is
kind of the the RICO statute of of
health care we have this law for reason
we have this law because earlier
whistleblowers have shown us that such a
law was necessary if this brings down
doctors neurosurgeons if it brings down
corporate leaders at UPMC health and
UPMC Medical Center then it needs to it
needs to be done all right
and just like to acknowledge that
there's a little bit of a problem with
the Commission but we're gonna keep on
in the past weeks of 2019 we had
WikiLeaks despite the fact that Julian
Assange is their founder is in jail
facing this extradition case for on 17
counts of violating the Espionage Act we
have an organization that has been under
attack still doing crucial work and
they've been working to expose fraud in
the organization for the prohibition of
chemical weapons investigation into an
alleged chemical attack in DOMA Syria in
April 2018 they released a fourth batch
of documents from whistleblowers and it
contained further proof victims in
videos that we all saw we're not
suffering from toxic chlorine gas as
symptoms were inconsistent we're also
finding that one of the engineers who
who is a whistleblower and this has had
his work suppressed and essentially was
informed or found out that his work was
going to be removed from a database so
that nobody knew that it had any
existence whatsoever that had not been
done in connection with this
investigation
I wonder what what are your comments on
this effort that WikiLeaks led them in
Alden to aid these professionals in
exposing what the OPCW did yeah this is
a far bigger deal than what this is 15
separate investigators objecting to the
fact that their analysis was either
taken out of context or it was falsified
entirely that the opcw's final analysis
of events on the ground following the
alleged we now know false chemical
attack in Douma took place the the
conclusion was that there was no
evidence to indicate that such an attack
took place that the the information was
falsified and it was the false
information that was used to come to a
political conclusion so the fact set
that means whistleblowers came out I
think is wonderful it was very it was
very brave back the fact that they had
to rely on WikiLeaks to do in that
sphere resides me but it also as you
pointed out serves to remind us not to
the canvas and they keep coming out with
these with these original first-person
documents proving that so much of what
we know from the mainstream media is
just a false narrative we wouldn't know
any of the story without WikiLeaks yeah
absolutely and I just wanted to mention
a quote from one of these documents that
was put up on leaks website where I
mentioned that expert stated that the
onset of excessive frothing as a result
of pulmonary edema observed in photos
and reported by witnesses would not
occur in the short time
from the reported occurrence of the
alleged incident and the time the videos
were recorded so approximately three to
four hours and then furthermore and this
is from a toxicology meeting that took
place June 2018 you see the experts were
also of the opinion it was highly
unlikely that victims would have
gathered in aisles at the center of
their respective apartments as such a
short distance from an escape from any
toxic chlorine gas to clean your air and
you also see things here like that
suggest it one of the other email
threads shared suggest that the death of
the circumstances of death for the
victims chlorine
rather than a corpse was arranged one of
the things that's been key about these
documents that's been showing is a very
likelihood that much of this that's
finished for us yeah it's funny that's
what the investigators said from the
very beginning and nobody paid any
attention to them so even after these
revelations from from WikiLeaks we see
shows like Morning Joe on MSNBC another
one is Ali Velshi on CNN repeating this
narrative that there was a chlorine gas
attack in do that the chlorine gas
attack was it just simply is not true in
a letter to the UK government we had UN
special rabbit or Niels Meltzer share
his strong objection to the UK
government's indifference toward Julian
Assange's ongoing abuse and mistreatment
this was a quote that was in his letter
no objective observer can escape the
conclusion that mr. Assange is that mr.
Assange is due process rights have been
seriously consistently and deliberately
violated in every phase of each judicial
proceeding conducted against him in all
involved jurisdictions as we had this
really strong letter and it was pointing
out how Julian Assange you know all of
this evidence of psychological torture
was brought to the attention of the UK
government and then yet they continue to
deny that any
such torture has taken place and in fact
Niels Meltzer doesn't stop at Assange's
abuse he also connects it to the fact
that the British government has done
nothing to comply with requests and/or
the effort of UN officials to urge the
British government to care about their
and their involvement in the torture and
rendition program and and so Niels
Meltzer connects their indifference to
Julian Assange as torture to their
indifference to getting accountability
or seeking accountability for torture
and rendition your comments John yeah
this is a an important statement coming
from the United Nations Special
Rapporteur I'm afraid that it's been
largely ignored at least by the US and
British governments I'm in touch with
Julian Assange's attorney he's and this
is a real concern that they have when we
read in the media for example Kevin that
Julian struggles to remember his own
name or that he is unable to participate
in his own defense they're serious about
this they're not making this up they're
not exaggerating there they're
experienced in their contacts with him
this is this is a real thing and it's
because the American and British
governments are are breaking him
mentally and emotionally they're doing
it deliberately they're doing it with
malice aforethought and the United
Nations thank goodness has recognized
that now what's more important is that
we need a judge to recognize that his
hearing for extradition of the United
States is coming up in February I know
that you'll be there these hearings
normally take up that's John normally
take about four hours this one is
scheduled to be something like four
weeks so perhaps there's a chance that
that something good may come of this I
don't know I don't think any of us know
including his own attorneys I was also
glad to see that the special repertoire
mentioned Chelsea Manning that Chelsea
Manning her treatment is also is also a
kin to torture chessy manny has not even
been charged with a crime she's being
held in
attempted court for refusing to testify
against Julian Assange before a grand
jury Jeremy Hammond the the famed
anonymous hacker is also being held
without charge for failing to to testify
against Julian and a grand jury these
grand juries are are renewed even after
their term runs out and as a result
people like Chelsea and Jeremy can be
held literally indefinitely now
Julian's already been charged with a
crime and there's a law in the United
States saying that a journey cannot be
I'm sorry a grand jury cannot be
impaneled or cannot continue to be
impaneled once the charges have been
levied well this tells me that either
the Department of Justice is breaking
the law in continuing to hold Chelsea
Jeremy or they intend to add additional
charges on to the two dozen plus charges
they've already filed against Julian
it's something that we probably won't
know the truth about until at least
February and probably March as you
mentioned Niels Meltzer also wrote a
letter to the US government on Manning's
coercive confinement and it's me the
first time that he put something
together importantly he references his
predecessor Juan Mendez who we both know
very well had determined that Manning
was tortured that if not cruelly and
humanely treated while she was confined
at Quantico after being arrested for
disclosing documents to Wikileaks and
Chelsea had her own reaction to all this
she said that I am thrilled to see the
practice of coercive confinement called
out for what it is incompatible with
international human rights standards
regardless even knowing I am very likely
to stay in jail for an even longer time
I'm never backing down and so that was a
big deal there we your your comments on
Chelsea anything else you might have to
add on Chelsea Manning you know I'm
gonna say Chelsea Manning has been
through a lot over the last decade
decade plus I have to say that I am
absolutely astounded
at the level of strength and metal that
she has displayed these these coercive
detentions are meant solely to break
people and to tell the truth Chelsea
could have gotten out of this early on
by playing a little game with the
prosecutors she could have gone before
that grand jury and answered every
question with the response I don't
recall
plain and simple and they would have had
to let her go she was offered immunity
and and refused the immunity saying that
immunity was unnecessary because
everything that they wanted to ask her
before the grand jury she had already
testified to in her own trial in a
military court and she urged them just
to take the transcript of her own
testimony and enter that into the record
so she could have a third thing is she
could have testified against Julian but
she stood up and she refused so this is
this is an unusual toughness this is a
toughness and fortitude that we don't
normally see on a day-to-day basis I
have mad respect for Chelsea Manning and
for the way she has stood up and one of
the things that we've been doing on the
show is we give people an update on the
amount of time that these cases that
we're following so before we move on to
the last looser discussions that we have
for the end of the show
it's 296 days that Chelsea Manning has
been in jail she owes a hundred and
eighty-seven thousand dollars in fines
now and of course we also know that
Julian Assange has now been in jail it's
going on nine months and he served a 50
week sentence for violating bail
conditions already and yet as
highlighted in Neil's Meltzer's letter
not released on house arrest
so unable to prepare an adequate defense
you mentioned jeremy hammond so jeremy
hammond is now in the alexandria
detention center that's the same one
that chelsea manning is being held and
and particularly for him it's important
for people to note that it's not clear
what is
up into his sentence because he was
originally sentenced to 10 years for
violating the Computer Fraud and Abuse
Act and so it's not clear if that
sentence has been suspended so that he
can be punished for contempt of grand
jury
do you know if no I don't know but
there's another important point there
I'm glad that you raised that because
you've reminded me Jeremy was
participating in something called our
death
that's the residential drug and alcohol
program
it's a Bureau of Prisons program that
allows you to go through something like
10 or 12 months of drug and alcohol
counseling the fact the matter is at
least in the prison that I was in you go
every week and you watch videotaped
episodes of intervention from ane that
counts as your drug and alcohol
counseling and then at the end of it you
have up to 18 months taken off your your
sentence but you have to complete the
whole year before you get the reward
well Jeremy had two months left to go in
his RDoc counseling they yanked him out
of our dad to send him to Alexandria
jail the the federal holding Center in
Alexandria Virginia where he's refusing
to testify in the grand jury against
Julian Assange that means that they have
effectively added 18 months to his
sentence so even if he had agreed to
testify this was just a way to screw
Jeremy Hammond and to lengthen his
sentence all right and then we'll also
just mention that reality winner is
serving her sentence and that that
continues and she's the NSA
whistleblower she's doing a sentence in
a facility in Texas Terri Albury is
still completing his sentence and he's
met by whistleblower and then so and
then there's another case but we'll get
to it at the end of the show so I wanted
to catch up with you because one thing
we mostly ignored on the show was this
Ukraine call whistleblower because it's
dominated attention and the whole
purpose of doing this show has been to
cover these whistleblower stories that
don't get covered in the media but I
wanted to talk with you because you were
one of the first people that I talked to
when it's all started to get reported
and like I wanted to know what you
thought about it and there's been
discussion about you know whether this
person is a whistleblower or not but you
know in the last week or two it's become
this big thing where Trump gets accused
of retaliating against the whistleblower
by naming the whistleblower the
Republicans go on Twitter and they share
a name and they get used of naming the
whistleblower it seems kind of silly but
then it also is connected to something
serious I think because we don't really
want public officials just outing what's
blowers randomly in order to go after
them and I think the biggest problem
that I have is that we have a clear case
here of a partisan whistleblower and so
it's been really difficult to figure out
what is the truth in all of this yeah
let me get one thing out of the way
right off the bat I'm on record you were
the first person I spoke to about this
but I'm on record as saying that I don't
believe that this is a real
whistleblower and it's not because the
whistleblower has taken one partisan
position or taken another partisan
position it's that there's a very
specific mo that one has to go through
to report waste fraud abuse or
illegality in the intelligence community
you go to your supervisor from there to
the Inspector General the Inspector
General then goes to the oversight
committees that's not what happened not
even remotely close to what happened in
this case in this case the whistleblower
went to his supervisor his supervisor
went to the Inspector General the
inspector general though then went to
the General Counsel's office the general
counsel went to the CIA leadership back
to the inspector general to the DNI
Inspector General and then not to the
oversight committees but to the Justice
Department so what we ended up with if
you read this
CIA whistleblower complaint is not a
straight account of what the
whistleblower claims to have seen or or
wants to reveal it's it's a very
legalistic document clearly written by a
team of
turnings now at the CIA on the analytic
side where this whistleblower supposedly
is you go through six months of writing
training at the CIA's famed training
facility called the farm known as the
farm and they do that because they want
every CIA analyst to write in exactly
the same style so that when the
president reads the the PDB the
president's Daily Brief every morning no
matter who wrote it it looks exactly the
same but this whistleblower complaint is
not in that CIA di writing style it's in
a style of attorneys and that tells me
that whatever information the
whistleblower initially reported or
wanted to report it was overtaken by the
CIA's general counsel and the CIA's
leadership and then reported back to the
DNI it never made its way to the
Oversight Committee like it was supposed
to and I believe that it was then it was
in part advocated so I don't take this
whistleblower seriously I actually went
on one of the new shows and said that I
didn't think it was a whistleblower I
thought it was an anonymous source for
the Democratic staff of the House
Intelligence Committee now with that
said and out of the way
I can't see any reason any legitimate
reason why you would have to reveal the
the identity of the whistleblower that
just doesn't make any sense to me now
internally in the CIA that
whistleblowers probably never going to
work in a serious job again even if he's
able to remain inside the CIA the battle
lines are gonna be drawn his career is
finished if his identity is revealed and
it pretty much already has been he's
gonna have trouble even getting
follow-on employment and that's just not
fair we can disagree about the the
methodology we can disagree about the
information or the import of the
information but ruining the guy on
purpose is is exactly what we should be
standing up and and opposing at least I
know you and I have opposed it from the
very beginning I think it's just wrong
yeah well and I think that one of the
things so there are two points and then
we'll move on to the last thing but
one issue is this tug-of-war between
whether it's journalism or whether it's
trying to out the person I think that if
you're a journalist you reasonably would
start to have questions about where this
person comes from who surrounds them
what was the genesis of this these
allegations and and how they came to be
public I think that's a fair thing to
explore now initially I guy remember
talking to you about the way the New
York Times went and reported it but that
was because they were just splashing
that this was a CIA person with no
context whatsoever and that was my
objection but I suppose a most
significant thing to talk about is this
narrative which is I suppose this you
can call whistleblower can now claim to
be hugely instrumental in the house
impeachment President Donald Trump and
and how should we process that yeah you
know it goes to motivation and
whistleblower attorneys will tell you
that motivation is irrelevant if a
person is reporting waste fraud abuse
illegality or threats to the public
health or public safety that's all that
matters
motivation is irrelevant to the to the
argument but you know I struggle with
that because in this case it seems to me
that motivation would be the heart of
the argument I would want to know what
the what the whistleblowers motivation
was because it would help me to conclude
whether or not it was a real
whistleblower but we we spent what a day
or two days on that issue when the New
York Times as you rightly say splashed
it on the front page and then everybody
just stopped talking about it and I
sorry do you think there's any merit to
Republicans complaining that they can't
interview this person or is it fair
because of the way we've seen behavior
reported for them to not have access to
this person no I think they should have
access you know when I blew the whistle
on the torture program I was subpoenaed
by the Senate Armed Services Committee
and I went up to the Armed Services
Committee and met with the staff for a
solid eight or nine hour
it was half Democratic and half
Republican we were in the vault the
skiff it's called so we can speak freely
we could speak you know in a classified
setting and the questions from both
sides were were all relevant they were
all down in the weeds they were all
investigative in nature and while I
fully recognized how partisan Capitol
Hill is especially at a time like this I
can't help but to think that the staffs
at least would have been professional
and the Republicans probably should have
had the opportunity to interview that
whistleblower all right so the last
thing that I wanted to talk to you about
involved this assassination of an
Iranian general that vividly played out
less than 24 hours ago and we learned
that Trump had himself apparently
authorized this drone strike on the
Iranian general it was in it was in
Baghdad it was on an airstrip that
apparently I understand he was killed
and the point I wanted to make with you
here was and how it relates to the show
is that we had a lot of whistleblowing
on this assassination complex as it's
been to thread or the drone programs
that the military as well as the CIA we
had a lot of public information that
warned us of what could happen if
somebody like president Donald Trump was
elected and was able to use this power
we criticized Barack Obama constantly
where his appointing himself judge jury
and executioner a lot of people who were
critics and these whistleblowers were
shooed away and told to buy it because
it was President Obama and he's a smart
person we should trust him and then it
turns out now is this is where we find
ourselves with a very dramatic
escalation that could be happening
between the u.s. and Iran your thoughts
yeah this is why we have such a great
debt of gratitude to people like David
Hale one of the the brave drone
whistleblowers he warned us that this
was going to happen and and you're
exactly right that we we
Barack Obama so much slack in this
illegal program you know it's it's not
legal to send drones to other countries
and to just rocket people without due
process without the the right to
confront their accusers in a court of
law before a jury of their peers whether
we like their politics are not as
irrelevant what's what what's relevant
is that they have the same
constitutional protections at least
they're supposed to that everybody else
has and so Barack Obama got away with it
for so long the inevitable continuation
was going to be Donald Trump getting
away with it and now we have Donald
Trump killing arguably the second most
important person in Iran a potential
successor to the supreme leader
Ayatollah Khamenei we're talking about
Qasem Soleimani
and there's there's going to be
retaliation you know an Iranian
journalist tweeted last night that he
asked Iranian officials isn't it true
that this is like killing Petraeus or
mattis and the response was no this is
far worse than killing Petraeus or
mattis this is like killing pence and so
you know everybody's talking about
de-escalation de-escalation is a pipe
dream Mike Pompeo the Secretary of State
and former CIA director was on Fox and
Friends this morning in which he said
incredibly we're we're in we're in you
know
Orwellian craziness right now he said
that that this was a move that was made
in order to help de-escalation and that
by killing silly money we saved untold
lives number of lives of Muslims and of
course all the all the nattering nabobs
on Fox just nodded their heads over and
over that like that made total sense
that by taking out the the number two
most powerful person in Iran that's
going to help bring peace to the region
and it's gonna make Muslims safer that's
what we're dealing with here yeah and we
also heard I believe from people like
Pompeo that they're going to wake up
in the morning and thanked us for what
we had done echoing dick cheney's
they'll be greeting us with liberators
when we come to Iraq and I think a good
point to close here is just to make it
abundantly clear that one of the things
we need most are whistleblowers from
military and yes these national security
or intelligence agencies who could come
forward right now and speak out about
what is happening we don't get that
enough but we also know in particular
with Iran what makes it so dangerous is
how both political parties are extremely
reluctant to be sober and objective in
their responses to the actions of the
Iranian government and other players in
Iran and we've seen in the last 10 to 20
years you know in public reporting a lot
of evidence of what the US has done
against Iran and they have a lot of
reason to view us as aggressors and this
kind of activity to constantly be
carried out by people in the Trump
administration it does not come without
consequences which is why it's important
for whistleblowers in the Trump
administration to be listened to if they
were to come forward and we need to pay
very very close attention to what the
Democratic candidates for president are
saying about this assassination
so far only Bernie Sanders and Tulsi
Gabbard have condemned it everybody else
and I'm talking from Joe Biden and
Elizabeth Warren on down they have all
fallen into line with the neoliberal
Pentagon intelligence community yeah I
believe Warren and Biden both echoed the
idea that he deserved to die yeah so
okay
although it's been it's been good to
have you on as a guest we Apollo was a
pleasure we apologize for the connection
issues earlier for those of you who have
been watching but it did get much better
in the last 20 15 or 20 minutes so
that's really great and it's always good
to talk to you so we'll have to have you
back on later on this year to go through
some more stories but thanks again John
and so you know what will happen links
to all the Articles that we mentioned
and again please hit that subscribe
button
lo follow us on Facebook and Twitter at
shadow proof come and support us for
even just a few dollars a month at
shadow proof calm / donate we have all
kinds of member perks from tote bags to
a member newsletter in a chatroom and
your donations will go directly to
keeping us online and funding reporting
from talented freelance journalists once
again I'm going to be going to London in
February February so your support is
going to help me be able to be there for
the three to four weeks that this
extradition hearing against Julian
Assange is expected to go so thanks
again everyone and please send us any
feedback and tell your friends about us
and have a great rest of your week